end of Chapter 12
this is a librivox recording all librivox recordings are in The public
domain for more information or to volunteer please visit librivox.org this recording by jay hall
The Wonderful Wizard of Oz by l frank Baum Chapter 13 The Rescue The Cowardly
Lion was much pleased to hear that the Wicked Witch had been melted by a bucket
of water, and Dorothy at once unlocked the gate of his prison and set him free.
They went in together to the castle, where Dorothy’s first act was to call
all the Winkies together and tell them that they were no longer slaves. There
was great rejoicing among the yellow Winkies, for they had been made to work
hard during many years for the Wicked Witch, who had always treated them with
great cruelty. They kept this day as a holiday, then and ever after, and spent
the time in feasting and dancing. “If our friends, the Scarecrow and the Tin
Woodman, were only with us,” said the Lion, “I should be quite happy.” “Don’t you
suppose we could rescue them?” asked the girl anxiously. “We can try,” answered the
Lion. So they called the yellow Winkies and asked them if they would help to
rescue their friends, and the Winkie said that they would be delighted to do all
in their power for Dorothy, who had set them free from bondage. So she chose a
number of the Winkies who looked as if they knew the most, and they all started
away. They traveled that day and part of the next until they came to the rocky
plain where the Tin Woodman lay, all battered and bent. His axe was near him,
but the blade was rusted and the handle broken off short. The Winkies lifted him
tenderly in their arms, and carried him back to the Yellow Castle again, Dorothy
shedding a few tears by the way at the sad plight of her old friend, and the
Lion looking sober and sorry. When they reached the castle Dorothy said to the
Winkies: “Are any of your people ten Smith's Oh, yes. Some of us are very good
ten Smiths they told her. “Then bring them to me,” she said. And when the ten Smith's
came, bringing with them all they're tools and baskets, she inquired,
“Can you straighten out those dents in the Tin Woodman, and bend him back into
shape again, and solder him together where he is broken?” The tinsmiths looked
the Woodman over carefully and then answered that they thought they could
mend him so he would be as good as ever.
So they set to work in one of the big yellow rooms of the castle and worked
for three days and four nights, hammering and twisting and bending and soldering
and polishing and pounding at the legs and body and head of the Tin Woodman,
until at last he was straightened out into his old form, and his joints worked
as well as ever. To be sure, there were several patches on him, but the ten
Smith's did a good job, and as the Woodman was not a vain man he did not
mine the patches at all. When, at last, he walked into Dorothy’s room and thanked
her for rescuing him, he was so pleased that he wept tears of joy, and Dorothy
had to wipe every tear carefully from his face with her apron, so that his
joints would not be rusted. At the same time her own tears fell thick and fast
at the joy of meaning her old friend again, and these tears did not need to be
wiped away. As for the Lion, he wiped his eyes so often with the tip of his tail
that it became quite wet, and he was obliged to go out into the courtyard and
hold it in the sun until it dried. “If we only had the Scarecrow with us again,”
said the Tin Woodman, when Dorothy had finished telling him everything that had
happened, “I should be quite happy.” “We must try to find him,” said the girl. So she
called the Winkies to help her, and they walked all that day and part of the next
until they came to the tall tree in the branches of which the Winged Monkeys had
tossed the Scarecrow’s clothes. It was a very tall tree, and the trunk was so
smooth that no one could climb it; but the Woodman said at once, “I’ll chop it
down, and then we can get the Scarecrow’s clothes.” Now while the tinsmiths had been
working on mending the Woodman himself, another of the Winkies, who was a
goldsmith, had made an axe handle of solid gold and fitted it to the
Woodman’s axe, instead of the old broken handle. Others polished the blade until
all the rust was room and it glistened like burnished silver.
As soon as he had spoke the Tin woman began to chop, and in a short time the
tree fell over with a crash, whereupon the Scarecrow’s clothes fell out of the
branches and rolled off on the ground.
Dorothy picked him up and had the Winkies carry them back to the castle,
where they were stuffed with nice, clean straw; and behold! here was his Scarecrow,
as good as ever, thanking them over and over again for saving him. Now that they were reunited,
Dorothy and her friends spent a few happy days at the Yellow Castle, where
they found everything they needed to make them comfortable. But one day the
girl thought of anonym and said, “We must go back to Oz, and claim his promise.” “Yes,”
said the Woodman, “at last I shall get my heart.” “And I shall get my brains out of
the Scarecrow joyfully. “And I shall get my courage,” said the Lion thoughtfully.
“And I shall get back to Kansas,” cried Dorothy, clapping her hands. “Oh, let us
start for the Emerald City tomorrow!” This they decided to do. The next day they
called the Winkies together and bade them goodbye The Winkies were sorry to
have them go, and they had grown so fond of the Tin Woodman that they begged him
to stay and rule over them and the Yellow Land of the West. Finding they
were determined to go, the Winkies gave Toto and the Lion each a golden collar;
and to Dorothy they presented a beautiful bracelet studded with diamonds;
and to the Scarecrow they gave a gold headed walking stick, to keep him from
stumbling; and to the Tin Woodman they offered a silver oil can inlaid with
gold and set with precious jewels. Every one of the travelers made the Winkies a
pretty speech in return, and all shook hands with him until their arms ached.
Dorothy went to the Witch’s cupboard to fill her basket with food for the
journey, and there she saw the Golden Cap.
She tried it on her own head and found that it fitted to her exactly. She did
not know anything about the charm of the Golden Cap, but she saw that it was
pretty, so she made up her mind to wear it and carry her Sun bonnet in the
basket. Then, being prepared for the journey, they all started for the Emerald City; and the
he's gave them three cheers and many good wishes to carry with them end of